I was raised by lesbians in the mountains,
قام على تنشئتي سحاقيات في الجبال
and I sort of came like a forest gnome to New York City a while back.
وجئت إلى مدينة نيويورك من الغابة منذ فترة قصيرة مثل جني
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Really messed with my head, but I'll get into that later.
في الواقع هذا سبب لي مشكلات ولكن سأنكلم عن ذلك لاحقًا.
I'll start with when I was eight years old.
سأبدأ حديثي منذ أن كان عمري ثمان سنوات.
I took a wood box,
أخذت صندوقا خشبيا،
and I buried a dollar bill, a pen and a fork inside this box in Colorado.
ودفنت دولارًا ورقيًا وقلماً و شوكة طعام داخل هذا الصندوق في كولورادو
And I thought some strange humanoids or aliens in 500 years would find this box
وفكرت في أن يجد الصندوق بعض أشباه البشر أو القادمين من الفضاء بعد 500 سنة
and learn about the way our species exchanged ideas,
ليتعلموا عن كيفية تبادل جنسنا لأفكاره
maybe how we ate our spaghetti.
أو عن كيفية أكلنا للسباغيتي.
I really didn't know.
أنا فعلا لم أعرف
Anyway, this is kind of funny,
وعلى أية حال أجد هذا مضحكًا
because here I am, 30 years later, and I'm still making boxes.
لأني الآن هنا و بعد 30 عاما لا أزال أصنع الصناديق
Now, at some point I was in Hawaii --
والآن ، في وقت ما كنت في هاواي
I like to hike and surf and do all that weird stuff,
أنا أحب التنزه والسفر والقيام بأعمال غريبة،
and I was making a collage for my ma.
كنت أصنع لأمي بعض الأعمال الفنية من الملصقات
And I took a dictionary and I ripped it up,
فأخذت قاموسًا ومزقته
and I made it into a sort of Agnes Martin grid,
وحولته إلى صندوق ملصقات
and I poured resin all over it and a bee got stuck.
وسكبت عليها صمغ الراتنج فالتصقت بها نحلة
Now, she's afraid of bees and she's allergic to them,
والآن ، هي تخشى النحل وعندها حساسية منه
so I poured more resin on the canvas, thinking I could hide it or something.
لذلك سكبت كمية أكبر من الراتنج على الصندوق معتقدًا أني سأخفيها أو شيء من هذا القبيل
Instead, the opposite happened:
ولكن ما حصل هو العكس
It sort of created a magnification,
أصبحت مكبَّرة
like a magnifying glass, on the dictionary text.
مثلما تكبر العدسة كلمات القاموس
So what did I do? I built more boxes.
إذا ماذا فعلت؟ لقد صنعت صناديق أكثر
This time, I started putting electronics, frogs,
وهذه المرة، بدأت بوضع إلكترونيات، وضفادع
strange bottles I'd find in the street -- anything I could find --
وزجاجات غريبة أجدها في الشارع وكل ما ما استطعت التقاطه
because I was always finding things my whole life,
لأنني طوال عمري دائمًا ما كنت أجد الأشياء
and trying to make relationships and tell stories between these objects.
وأحاول خلق علاقة بين هذه الأشياء وحكاية قصص عنها
So I started drawing around the objects,
وهكذا بدأت ارسم عن هذه الأشياء
and I realized: Holy moly, I can draw in space!
وهكذا اكتشفت أن بإمكاني الرسم في الفضاء بروعة
I can make free-floating lines,
أسنطيع أن أرسم خطوطًا متعرجة
like the way you would draw around a dead body at a crime scene.
كالتي تُرسم حول الجثة في مسرح الجريمة
So I took the objects out,
وأخرجت الأشياء إلى الحياة،
and I created my own taxonomy of invented specimens.
وخلقت تصنيفي الخاص للنماذج التي اخترعتها
First, botanical -- which you can kind of get a sense of.
أولا: النباتية التي يمكن معرفتها نوعا ما
Then I made some weird insects and creatures.
ثم صنعت تصنيفًا لبعض الحشرات و المخلوقات الغريبة
It was really fun; I was just drawing on the layers of resin.
وفعلا كان ذلك ممتعا، كنت فقط أرسم على طبقات الراتنج
And it was cool, because I was actually starting to have shows and stuff,
وكان ذلك رائعا فعلا، كنت فعلا قد بدأت في عرضها و غير ذلك
I was making some money, I could take my girlfriend for dinner,
بدأت أحصل على النقود، وأستطعت أن أصطحب صديقتي للعشاء
and like, go to Sizzler.
وأن أذهب إلى المطاعم
It was some good shit, man.
كان ذلك هراءً جيدًا يا رجل
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
At some point, I got up to the human form,
وفي نقطة معينة وصلت إلى الشكل البشري
life-size resin sculptures with drawings of humans inside the layers.
تماثيل بالحجم الطبيعي بالراتنج ورسوم البشر داخل طبقاته
This was great, except for one thing:
وكان هذا رائعا بإستثناء شيء واحد ..
I was going to die.
أني كنت سأموت.
I didn't know what to do, because the resin was going to kill me.
لم أعرف ما يجب علي فعله لأن الراتنج كان سيقتلني
And I went to bed every night thinking about it.
وكنت أذهب للفراش كل ليلة وأنا أفكر بذلك
So I tried using glass.
وهكذا حاولت استخدام الزجاج.
I started drawing on the layers of glass,
قبدأت بالرسم على طبقات الزجاج
almost like if you drew on a window, then you put another window,
وكأنما ترسم على نافذة ثم تضع نافذة آخرى
and another window, and you had all these windows together
ثم نافذة آخرى ثم تجمع كل هذه النوافذ معا
that made a three-dimensional composition.
وينتج هذا تشكيلا مجسما بثلاثة أبعاد
And this really worked, because I could stop using the resin.
وقد اثمر هذا فعلا فقد توقفت عن استعمال الراتنج
So I did this for years,
فعلت هذا لسنوات
which culminated in a very large work, which I call "The Triptych."
وكانت النتيجة عملاً كبيراً جدًا أسميه "اللوح الثلاثي"
"The Triptych" was largely inspired
وقد استوحيتُ فكرة "اللوح الثلاثي" من
by Hieronymus Bosch's "[The] Garden of Earthly Delights,"
من "حديقة المسرات الأرضية" لهيرونيموس بوش
which is a painting in the [Museo del] Prado in Spain.
وهي لوحة في متحف برادو في أسبانيا
Do you guys know this painting?
هل تعرفون هذه اللوحة؟
Good, it's a cool painting.
جيد، إنها لوحة رائعة
It's kind of ahead of its time, they say.
ويقولون إنها سابقة لزمانها
So, "The Triptych." I'll walk you through this piece.
"اللوح الثلاثي" سأسير بكم خلال هذه القطعة
It weighs 24,000 pounds.
التي وزنها 24000 رطل
It's 18 feet long.
وطولها 18 قدما
It's double-sided, so it's 36 feet of composition.
ولها جانبين مما يجعلها تتألف من 36 قدما
It's kind of weird.
إنها غريبة نوعا ما
Well, that's the blood fountain.
حسنا ، هناك نافورة دم
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
To the left, you have Jesus and the locusts.
تشاهدون في اليسار المسيح والجراد
There's a cave
وهناك كهف
where all these animal-headed creatures travel between two worlds.
حيث تسافر تلك المخلوقات ذات الرؤوس الحيوانية بين عالمين
They go from the representational world,
يذهبون من العالم التمثيلي
to this analog-mesh underworld, where they're hiding.
إلى العالم الشبكي المناظر حيث يختبؤون
This is where the animal-headed creatures are by the lighthouse,
هنا تقف المخلوقات ذات الرؤوس الحيوانية قريبا من الفنار الضوئي
and they're all about to commit mass suicide into the ocean.
وهي جميعا تتأهب للانتحار الجماعي في المحيط
The ocean is made up of thousands of elements.
والمحيط مصنوع من آلاف العناصر
This is a bird god tied up to a battleship.
وهذا إله طائر مربوط على باخرة حربية
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Billy Graham is in the ocean;
وهذا بيللي غراهام في المحيط
the Horizon from the oil spill; Waldo; Osama Bin Laden's shelter --
وهذا هو الزيت المتسرب وهذا والدو ، وهنا مأوى أسامة بن لادن
there's all kinds of weird stuff that you can find
وهناك كل أصناف الأشياء الغريبة التي قد تجدها
if you look really hard, in the ocean.
لو دققت النظر جيدا في المحيط
Anyway, this is a lady creature.
على العموم هذه سيدة مخلوقة
She's coming out of the ocean, and she's spitting oil into one hand
إنها تخرج من المحيط وهي تبصق زيتا في أحد كفيها
and she has clouds coming out of her other hand.
ولديها غيوم تخرج من كفها الآخر
Her hands are like scales,
وكفيها كالميزان
and she has the mythological reference of the Earth and cosmos in balance.
وهي تمثل الحالة الاسطورية للتوازن بين الأرض والكون
So that's one side of "The Triptych."
إذًا هذا جانب واحد من "اللوح الثلاثي"
It's a little narrative thing.
وهو أشبه بالحكاية
That's her hand that she's spitting into.
وهذا كفها الذي تبصق فيه
And then, when you go to the other side,
وبعد ذلك عندما تذهب إلى الجانب الآخر
she has like a trunk, like a bird's beak,
سيكون لها خرطوم مثل منقار الطير
and she's spitting clouds out of her trunk.
وهي تنفث الغيوم من خرطومها
Then she has an 18-foot-long serpent's tail that connects "The Triptych."
ثم إن لديها ذيل ثعبان طوله 18 قدما يربط "اللوح الثلاثي"
Anyway, her tail catches on fire from the back of the volcano.
ويحترق ذيلها بالنار من وراء البركان
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I don't know why that happened.
ولا أدري لم حدث ذلك
That happens, you know.
وهذا يحدث كما تعلمون.
Her tail terminates in a cycloptic eyeball,
وينتهي ذيلها بعين منفردة
made out of 1986 terrorist cards.
مصنوعة من 1986 بطاقة إرهابي
Have you guys seen those?
هل رأيتم هؤلاء؟
They were made in the 1980's, they're like baseball cards of terrorists.
قد تم صنعهم في الثمانينات وتشبه بطاقات كرة البيسبول الخاصة بالإرهابيين
Way ahead of their time.
سابقين زمنهم بوقت طويل.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
That will bring you to my latest project.
وهذا سيأتي بكم إلى مشروعي الأخير
I'm in the middle of two projects:
أنا الآن في منتصف مشروعين
One's called "Psychogeographies."
أحدهما يسمى "الجغرافيا النفسية"
It's about a six-year project to make 100 of these humans.
ويدور حول مشروع الست سنوات لصناعة 100 من هؤلاء البشر
Each one is an archive of our culture,
وكل واحد منهم أرشيفا لحضارتنا
through our ripped-up media and matter,
من خلال إعلامنا و مواضيعنا المتهرئة
whether it's encyclopedias or dictionaries or magazines.
وإن كانت موسوعات أو قواميس أو مجلات
But each one acts as a sort of an archive in the shape of a human,
ولكن كل واحد سيمثل نوعا من الأرشيف على شكل إنسان
and they travel in groups of 20, 4, or 12 at a time.
ويتنقلون في مجموعات من 20 أو 4 أو 12
They're like cells -- they come together, they divide.
إنهم مثل الخلايا -- يأتون معا و ينقسمون
And you kind of walk through them. It's taking me years.
وستمشي بينهم ويستغرق ذلك سنينا
Each one is basically a 3,000-pound microscope slide
وكل واحد منهم هو فلم شفاف ميكروسكوبي يزن 3000 رطلا
with a human stuck inside.
وداخله إنسان عالق
This one has a little cave in his chest.
ولهذا الإنسان كهف في صدره
That's his head; there's the chest, you can kind of see the beginning.
وهذا رأسه و هنا صدره و ترون البداية شكل ما
I'm going to go down the body for you:
و سأذهب نزولاً على الجسم لأجلكم
There's a waterfall coming out of his chest,
و هناك شلال ماء يخرج من صدره
covering his penis -- or not-penis, or whatever it is,
ليغطي قضيبه أو ليس قضيبه أو مهما كان
a kind of androgynous thing.
فقد يكون شيئا مخنثا
I'll take you quickly through these works,
وسأقودكم بسرعة خلال هذه الأعمال
because I can't explain them for too long.
لأنني لا أستطيع شرحها لفترة طويلة
There are the layers, you can kind of see it.
هناك الطبقات التي قد يمكنكم رؤيتها
That's a body getting split in half.
وهذا جسم ينقسم بالنصف
This one has two heads,
و هذا له رأسين
and it's communicating between the two heads.
وهو يتواصل بين الرأسين
You can see the pills coming out,
و تشاهدون حبوب الدواء تخرج منه
going into one head from this weird statue.
وتذهب إلى أحد الرأسين من التمثال الغريب
There's a little forest scene inside the chest cavity.
وهناك منظر لغابة صغيرة في كل كهف صدري
Can you see that?
هل يمكنكم مشاهدة ذلك؟
Anyway, this talk's all about these boxes,
وعلى أية حال يدور الحديث حول هذه الصناديق
like the boxes we're in.
مثل الصناديق التي نحن فيها
This box we're in, the solar system is a box.
هذا الصندوق الذي نحن فيه، النظام الشمسي صندوق.
This brings you to my latest box.
وهذا يأخذكم إلى صندوقي الأخير
It's a brick box. It's called Pioneer Works.
إنه صندوق من الطوب ويُسمى أعمال الرواد
(Cheers)
(هتاف و تشجيع)
Inside of this box is a physicist,
و داخل هذا الصندوق يوجد طبيب،
a neuroscientist, a painter, a musician,
وعالم أعصاب، ورسام، وموسيقار،
a writer, a radio station, a museum, a school,
وكاتب، ومحطة إذاعية، ومتحف، ومدرسة،
a publishing arm to disseminate all the content we make there into the world;
و قسم للنشر لتوزيع كل المحتويات التي نضيفها إلى العالم
a garden.
وحديقة
We shake this box up,
و نهز هذا الصندوق
and all these people kind of start hitting each other like particles.
ويبدأ كل هؤلاء الناس بالأصطدام ببعضهم مثل الجزيئات
And I think that's the way you change the world.
وأنا أعتقد بأن هذه هي الطريقة التي تغير العالم
You redefine your insides and the box that you're living in.
تعيدون تشكيل دواخلكم و الصناديق التي تعيشون فيها
And you come together to realize that we're all in this together,
و تأتون معا لتتبينوا بأننا جميعا في هذا معا
that this delusion of difference --
وإن وهم الاختلافات
this idea of countries, of borders, of religion -- doesn't work.
وفكرة الدول والحدود والأديان لا فائدة منها
We're all really made up of the same stuff, in the same box.
إننا جميعا مصنوعون من نفس المواد وفي نفس الصندوق
And if we don't start exchanging that stuff sweetly and nicely,
وإذا لم نبدأ بإستبدال هذا الهراء بنعومة وسلاسة
we're all going to die real soon.
فإننا جميعا سنموت فعليًا قريبًا
Thank you very much.
أشكركم كثيرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)